Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
- Series II. Lolita Correspondence between Olympia Press, Clairouin, and Vladimir Nabokov
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel February 2, 1960 to March 8, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    8 items (3 TLS, 5 TL). G. objects to VN's lawyer's opinion that the original contract between VN and Olympia does not cover editions "a bon marché" (2.2.60) Correspondence between Odette Hummel and Clairouin re the translation rights for Lolita, which Hummel has some claim to.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel March 11, 1960 to April 6, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    8 items (2 TLS, 4 TL, 2 bank statements, with autograph calculations). Concerns the financial arrangements with Odette Hummel.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel April 6, 1960 to May 12, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    10 items (4 TLS, 5 TL, 1 statement). Concerning the contract with Mondadori, especially the payment due Hummel. Mention of the Japanese and Swedish translation rights. Mention of William Burroughs' Naked Lunch, which Olympia also publishes and would like Mondadori to publish.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel May 16, 1960 to June 27, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    12 items (6 TLS, 6 TL). Regarding the financial matters re: translation of Lolita into Japanese, Italian, Spanish, Finnish, Portuguese, Hebrew etc. Discussing course of action with regard to the pirated editions of Lolita. in Lebanon (which action VN would like G. to disassociate himself from).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel July 1, 1960 to November 15, 1960. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    12 items (4 TLS, 6 TL, 1 statement, 1 receipt). G. asks (7.1.60) once more for copies of the Swedish contracts and all other such translation contracts, or he will be forced to commence litigation, which in fact he does later initiate (8.30.60). Regulation of various financial matters.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel November 15, 1960 to February 1, 1961. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    11 items (4 TLS, 3 TL, 3 statements, 1 autograph calculations). Various statements of earnings, royalties due etc. Repeated request by G., on behalf of Hummel, for statements from the Brazilian, Finnish, Danish, Norwegian, Argentine, German, Israeli, Swedish and Greek publishers.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, February 6, 1961 to April 24, 1961. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    14 items (5 TLS, 9 TL, including copies of 3 of the TLS). Continuing dispute over payments (especially re Rowohlt) from and to Olympia. Litigation is imminent, with mention of meetings between lawyers. Unpleasant exchange between Girodias and Ergaz over a Playboy article, of whose appearance neither Ergaz nor VN were informed (4.20.61 & 4.24.61). G. claims that he was forced to such tactics by the nature of his relationship with VN, a relationship whose regrettably negative character is altogether VN's fault (4.24.61). Reference to meeting with VN in which the latter apparently refused to acknowledge G. Includes carbon of letter G. is sending to Mr. Spectorsky (of Playboy).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel, May 3, 1961 to June 20, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    10 items (3 TLS, 6 TL, including copies of 3 TLS and 1 TL, with 1 statement). Regarding arrangements with Odette Hummel. G. threatens action over VN and Clairouin's non-payment.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel, June 21, 1961 to August 24, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    9 items (4 TLS, 4 TL, and 1 statement). Concerns both VN and G.'s deliberate non-payment of the sums owed each other, which is causing problems for Odette Hummel. Litigation between Olympia and VN continues.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, November 16, 1961 to November 24, 1961. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    5 items (3 TLS with enclosure, 2 TL). Concerning contracts with Weidenfeld & Nicolson and with Putnam's, and discussing some new "imbroglio" which Schébéko does not quite comprehend. Deals with some accounting matters.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel December 14, 1961 to March 28, 1962. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    8 items (1 TLS, 3 TL, 3 typed statements and 1 autograph statement on graph paper). Settling various financial affairs. Hummel notifies Clairouin that she has not received any statements from Rowohlt (4.10.62).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel, April 5, 1962 to September 26, 1962. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    14 items (5 TLS, 9 TL). Letter from Mairesse informing G. that the film version of Lolita has just been released in New York. Includes a list of foreign contracts.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel October 3, 1962 to December 31, 1962. (Box 3, Folder 31)
    11 items (1 TLS, 9 TL, 1 receipt). Concerning primarily payment to Odette Hummel and other accounting matters re: Lolita. Includes a list of foreign contracts (attached to 9.21.62).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Hummel, January 1963 to April 29, 1964. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    9 items (1TLS, 8 TL). Discussing various financial affairs (the Corgi and Greek editions of Lolita).
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel, May 4, 1963 to August 7, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    9 items (2 TLS, 5 TL, 1 statement, 1 receipt). Letters enclosing or including statements of sales for foreign editions of Lolita. 8.5.63 and 8.6.63 discussing briefly some difficulty with the Rowohlt account.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel, August 26, 1963 to December 18, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    7 items (6 TL, 1 statement). Letters enclosing or including statement of sales both of translations of Lolita and of Olympia's edition of the same.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel, January 1964 to June 4, 1964. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    10 items (1 TLS, 9 TL). Concerning a delay in the provision of Olympia's statement (3.12.64, 4.29.64, 5.27.64); other transactions with Hummel.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, and Odette Hummel, June 11, 1964 to April 23, 1965. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    12 items (12 TL). Letters enclosing or including statements of sales for foreign editions of Lolita; all transactions involving Hummel.
  - Correspondence between Olympia Press, and the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin, July 27, 1965 to February 14, 1968. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    9 items (3 TLS, 4 TL, 2 statements). Discussing the new legal dispute between VN and Olympia. VN considers his contract with Olympia terminated (7.27.65), while G., who claims not to have been notified of this litigation (12.6.65 - something denied by Schébéko in 12.17.65), warns Schébéko that, as she is also Olympia's agent, she may be guilty of conflict of interest. Statements of money owed Olympia.
  - Misc. correspondence between Olympia and Bureau littéraire D. Clairouin, July 11, 1955 to November 7, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    6 items (2 TLS, 4 TL). Concerning various texts either being published by Olympia or represented by Clarouin.
  - Miscellaneous items, undated. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    15 items. Calculations and notes scribbled in pencil or pen on paper and on the back of what appear to be a novel by Douglas Woolf, Fade Out, an unidentifable French work, and a notice about Pogo books. Two of Maurice Girodias' business cards. Two postal service tickets.
- Series III. Lolita Miscellaneous 1945-1970 (Correspondence, Statements, Publicity, Contracts, Legal Documents)
  - Correspondence and statements from foreign-language publishers, 1945 to 1959. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    7 items (including one autograph note). Statements and correspondence from Mondadori (Italy), Steingrüber (?), Reitzel (Denmark), Steimatzki, and Uitgeverij Oitsterwijk. All but one for Lolita.
  - Correspondence and statements to and from foreign-language publishers, July 1960 to June 1961. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    11 items. Statements and correspondence to and from SUR, Editora Civilizacao Brazileira, Gerolymbos (Greece), Uitgerverij Oisterwijk (Netherland), Bar David (Israel), Cappelens (Norway). All re Lolita.
  - Correspondence and statements from foreign-language publishers, August 1961 to last quarter 1961. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    8 items. Statements and correspondence to and from SUR, Rowohlt (Germany), Bonnier (Sweden), Reitzel (Denmark), Sagan (Israel). All re Lolita.
  - Correspondence and statements from foreign-language publishers, 1962 to 1963. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    5 items (including 1 autograph note). Statements and correspondence from Tutle (Japan), Jaico (India), Boa Leitura Editora (Brazil), Transworld, and Mondadori.
  - Correspondence and statements to from foreign-language publishers, 1964 to 1967. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    10 items. Statements and correspondence from Jaico (India), Mondadori, Gummerus (Finland), and Uitgeverig Oisterwijk.
  - Publicity material from Olympia, 1955 to 1958. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    8 items: (1) a "Note" (in French) concerning a "collection of books on art and archaeology" published by Olympia. (2) a list of newspapers/magazines/journals, with the heading " Lolita: Liste des services de presse." (3) a newspaper clipping (in French) referencing John Gordon's attack on Lolita, summarizing the novel's plot as a tale of love between a middle aged man and a girl of six, and locating Cornell in Boston. (4) a letter (in French) to the Minister of the Interior by G.'s lawyer, Jean Lemanissier, in response to the anticipated banning of Lolita and 20 other of Olympia's publications (12.10.56). Accompanied a letter by Doussia Ergaz to M. Monneray (12.19.56). (5) a press release (in French) explaining Olympia's position with regard to the upcoming legal proceedings. Includes a selection of press commentary (1.18.57). (6) a press release (in French) explaining Olympia's position with regard to the January 28 legal proceedings. May be incomplete (1.29.57). (7) a letter (in French) announcing an upcoming court date, and outlining the history of the Lolita controversy (1.4.58). (8) a press release (in French) outlining Lolita's history in the courts, and citing Girodias' defense of this novel and the other literature that Olympia publishes.
  - Publicity material from Olympia Press, 1959. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    2 items: (1) 5 page press release (in French) that appears just prior to the release of Gallimard's edition of Lolita. Traces both publication and legal history of Lolita. Ends by congratulating Gallimard for its "act of courage" in publishing a work described as "unhealthy", and by calling for the lifting of the second ban on the novel. (2) an open letter (in English) to the French government calling for the lifting of the ban on Lolita in the name of those great writers (Lawrence, Joyce) who have been well-served by France's "hospitality."
  - Publicity material from Olympia, 1961 to 1962. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    3 items: (1) a press release (in French) explaining Olympia's position with regard to the upcoming legal proceedings (March 14). Mentions a letter of protest signed by about thirty American and British authors, including Bertrand Russell, Rosamond Lehmann, E. M. Forster, Ivy-Compton-Burnett, Lawrence Durrell, Arthur Miller, Osbert Sitwell, and Graham Greene. (2) Girodias' Playboy article from April 1961. (3) a letter (in English and French), possibly to booksellers (?) explaining that orders for Lolita should be addressed to Corgi Books (London). Includes list of other publications by Olympia, including The Secret Life of Robinson Crusoe, The Memoirs of Fanny Hill, and Helen and Desire (12.62). With Olympia "Price-List & Order-Form" attached.
  - Contract with Steimatzki, February 5, 1959. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Photocopy of contract with Steimatzki for the Israeli publication in English of Lolita. With letter from Girodias to Steimatzki attached.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, 1958. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    3 items: (1) a chronology of the relationship between VN and Olympia ending in 1957 (2 copies). (2) TLS from Emile-Jean Bomsel, Girodias' lawyer (1.2.58). (3) a list of questions posed by Clairouin (?) (1.3.58).
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, January 20, 1958 to January 27, 1958. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    2 items: (1) a letter from Ergaz to her friend Henri Motulsky, asking his opinion in the VN case. (2) a letter from Henri Motulsky to Ergaz, outlining his view of the case (2 copies).
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, February 10, 1958 to January 17, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    9 items. Includes: (1) subpoenas dated 2.10.58 and 1.2.61 (2 copies of latter, 1 enclosed within (4)). (2) letter from Ergaz to Motulsky hoping that VN has now decided to relinquish legal action (she implies that VN has been acting in a rather childish way) (3.7.58). (3) letter from Motulsky and Ergaz expressing his relief, as he did not think the legal prospects looked good (3.17.58). (4) letter to Jacques Mercier, enclosing (1).
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, January 19, 1961 to February 23, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    13 items. Includes: (1) 7 TL from Marie Schébéko to Jacques Mercier discussing VN's wishes (the Nabokovs would now like to resolve matters without resorting to lawryers), and expressing, among other things, exasperation with this difficult client. (2) a summons to force Olympia to pay what it owes. (3) 3 TL to VéN. (4) 2 TL to VN.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, March 2, 1961 to March 24, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    14 items. Includes: (1) 3 TLS from Mercier to Schébéko answering questions having to do with the action against Olympia. (2) 3 TL from Schébéko to Mercier thanking him for his advice. (3) 4 TL to VéN, 1 TL to VN.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, March 27, 1961 to April 25, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    13 items, including letters to VéN, to and from Mercier, to Touraille and Castelain. Includes copy of a subpoena delivered to Olympia.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, April 27, 1961 to November 16, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    14 items, including letters from Jacques Mercier (the latter answering questions posed by the Nabokovs and thus allowing Schébéko to put an end to her clients' "harassment"), and from Schébéko passing on the Nabokovs' anxiety over the suspect commitment of Castelain
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, November 25, 1961 to April 17, 1962. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    12 items, including letters to and from Touraille, Mercier, and Castelain, and to VN, answering several of VN 's questions, and eventually setting the terms for the peaceful resolution of the case.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, December 30, 1964 to July 28, 1965. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    8 items, including a dossier of correspondence between the Nabokovs, Olympia and Clairouin sent to Maître Shirman. Other letters and a subpoena re: the Nabokovs' most recent claim of rupture.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, August 6, 1965 to November 30, 1966. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    19 items, including 4 legal documents.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, December 7, 1966 to June 6, 1967. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    7 items, including 4 legal documents outlining the decision to declare the contract between VN and Olympia annulled as of December 14, 1964.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, June 15, 1967 to October 24, 1969. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    11 items, including 1 legal document (a notice of Olympia's appeal), and correspondence between Schébéko and Roger Hennuyer, the lawyer she has asked to represent her in this latest stage of the Lolita affair.
  - Documents from legal proceedings between Olympia, Clairouin and Vladimir Nabokov, October 27, 1969 to April 20, 1970. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    12 items, including 1 legal document, concerning the failure of Olympia's appeal. Correspondence between Schébéko and Raymond Gaultier, her lawyer, over his fees, which, Schébéko believes, ought to have been paid by Olympia.
- Series IV. Outgoing Correspondence from Véra Nabokov 1949-1977
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, December 6, 1949 to March 10, 1952. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    5 TLS, in French, discussing various contractual matters, especially the tangled question of the contract with Table Rond and VN's relationship with Gallimard. Some discussion of translation.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, April 21, 1952 to May 12, 1952. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    3 TLS with contract attached, in French, concerning the contract with Table Rond which has been complicated by a prior contract with Gallimard. Autograph annotations.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, June 6, 1952 to September 11, 1952. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    6 TLS, in French, written mostly from various points west of Ithaca, concerning the contract with Table Rond, the American publication of The Defense, and the translation of The Gift (Vladimir pressing as always for Jarl Priel, somewhat to Véra's amusement). Some autograph annotations.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, January 28, 1953 to September 17, 1954. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    4 TLS, in French, concerning the translation of Despair, Conclusive Evidence and The Gift, and the possibility of publishing a new novel outside the US if "moral considerations" prevent its publication within the States.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, May 5, 1955 to November 19, 1955. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    5 TLS, in French, mostly concerning the publication of Lolita with Olympia, especially Girodias' suggestion that all French in the original be cut, the future French translation of the novel, and VN's concern over the copyright and G.'s tardiness in sending proofs. Discussion of contractual and translation matters involving other works, including Laughter in the Dark, The Defense, Pnin, Conclusive Evidence.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, January 15, 1956 to April 21, 1956. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    8 TLS, in French, mostly concerning Lolita, including the positive reviews by Graham Greene and Harvey Breit (cites portions of the latter's review in The New York Times Book Review), as well as the American publication rights. Some discussion of the growing rift between Girodias and VN.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, June 12, 1956 to November 8, 1956. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    5 TLS, in English and French, mainly regarding negotiations with American firms for the publication of Lolita. Expresses her and her husband's concern that Girodias has apparently deceived Ergaz about the existence of a clause that would have prohibited G. from negotiating contracts for Lolita. without VN's consent. Asserts inevitability of prosecution when Lolita. is published in the States, and reminds Ergaz that the interim copyright allows only 1500 copies of the novel to be imported. Includes a typed copy of Howard Nemerov's letter to the NY Times protesting the "vicious absurdity" of the censorship of Lolita. Autograph annotations.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, November 19, 1956 to December 31, 1956. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    6 TLS, in English and French, concerning issues surrounding the American publication of Lolita (including the publication of a portion in The Anchor Review), Girodias' plan of importing copies of Lolita. into the U.S., and negotiations with a German firm over the rights to other works. Véra expresses astonishment that the authorities cannot distinguish between a "masterpiece like Lolita and certain books that are written only to scandalize."
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, January 21, 1957 to June 1, 1957. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    6 TLS, concerning the American publication of Lolita (by June, Doubleday has made an offer), and detailing the continuing contract woes with Girodias. Also discusses contractual and translation matters around Pnin, and Invitation. Brief discussion of the French translator for Lolita (VN has been reading samples).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, June 11, 1957 to February 27, 1958. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    6 TLS, in French and English, discussing contracts and negotiations with foreign publishing houses (Rowohlt, SUR etc). Letter (7.30.57) discussing Girodias' obnoxious demands re the American publication of Lolita
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, March 1, 1958 to June 8, 1958. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    7 TLS, in French, concerning contract with Rowohlt, the French translation of Lolita (especially slow speed at which Kahane appears to be working), bad relations with Girodias which predate G.'s conduct over Doubleday, negotiation of translation and rights with SUR (Buenos Aires),
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, July 8, 1958 to October 7, 1958. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    5 TLS, 1 TL, in French, concerning the British publication of Lolita (VN authorized Walter Minton find a publisher, perhaps Bodley Head, perhaps Weidenfeld & Nicolson), as well as continuing difficulties with Girodias. Mentions several good American reviews of Lolita, and asks for more information regarding the new banning of Lolita. Annotations.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz, November 14, 1958 to December 2, 1958. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    7 TLS, in French and English, discussing various contractual and translation matters re Lolita, including VN's belief that Kahane will never finish his translation of Lolita. (it has been 2 years), foreign contracts with Mondadori, Rowolht, Cappelen etc. VN refuses to consider some omissions proposed by Mondadori, as there are no obscene passages in Lolita. Notes various minor disputes with Girodias. Véra notes in a number of letters the couple's extreme business.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, December 3, 1958 to December 30, 1958. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    6 TLS, in French and English, regarding the publication of Lolita in Norway, Japan, Israel (English, Hebrew, Polish) and Argentina, as well as the French translation by Kahane.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, January 6, 1960 to January 18, 1960. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    5 TLS, 2 TL fragments, in French, concerning film rights, foreign publication rights and accounting for Lolita and other works (including Conclusive Evidence, Invitation, Laughter in the Dark, Pnin, and The Defense). Mentions car accident that has killed Camus, and wonders whether the Gallimards injured were members of Gaston Gallimard's family.